Guide to the Brantley York Records and Papers, 1838 - 1966 UA.03.50.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Brantley York records and papers
1838 - 1966
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
York, Brantley, 1805-1891
UA.03.50.0001
0.3 Linear Feet
Brantley York was an educator, author, and Methodist clergyman in North Carolina. He organized Union Institute Academy at Brown's Schoolhouse in Randolph Co., N.C. in 1839, which would evolve into Normal College, Trinity College, and later Duke University. York also wrote an English grammar, as well as several other instructional textbooks. The Brantley York Records and Papers contain correspondence, a grade book, certificates, manuscripts, and published works. Modern materials were added to the collection; these include York family genealogical information, as well as clippings about York and his activities. Major subjects include the early history of Union Institute, Normal College, Trinity College and Duke University; education in North Carolina in the 19th century; and the Methodist Episcopal Church, South. English.
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
No restrictions.
Provenance
The Brantley York Records and Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer.
Biographical Note
A largely self-taught educator, Methodist minister, and author of a series of English grammars, Brantley York (1805-1891) was asked by Methodist and Quaker farmers in rural Randolph County, N.C. to help provide education for their sons and daughters. At the site of the former Brown's Schoolhouse, he organized Union Institute Academy in 1838 and met with instant success, building two new buildings within a year-and-a-half. Though gratified at his accomplishment, he worked extremely hard raising money, and he began to go blind working late at night preparing recitations in subjects he had not adequately studied. In fact, he recorded in his diary a statement saying he considered his years at Union Institute to be "truly onerous." York, however, had found his life's work at Union Institute and though completely blind by age forty-eight, he lived to be eighty-six and founded half-a-dozen schools, lectured over 8,000 times, and taught more than 15,000 pupils. He served as Principal of Union Institute from 1838 to 1842.
Duke University (Durham, N.C.) was established in 1924 and evolved from the following institutions: Brown's Schoolhouse (Randolph Co., N.C.) 1838-1839; Union Institute (Randolph Co., N.C.) 1839-1851; Normal College (Randolph Co., N.C.) 1851-1859; Trinity College (Randolph Co., N.C.) 1859-1892 and (Durham, N.C.) 1892-1924.
Collection Overview
The Brantley York Records and Papers include correspondence, clippings, a grade book, certificates, manuscripts, and published works. Modern materials were added to the collection; these include York family genealogical information, as well as clippings about York and his activities. Preservation photocopies of all deteriorating clippings have been made for patron use.
The first series, Brantley York papers, includes certificates and other documents, a small amount of correspondence, and a grade book. The second series, Writings, features manuscript drafts and a published copy of York's autobiography, as well as copies of three of his instructional texts. The final series contains both contemporary and modern clippings about Brantley York's life, work, and family members. Also included in this series is a York family genealogy.
Related Material
[Forms part of:] Duke University President records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Trinity College (Randolph Co., N.C.) Collection
University Archives, Duke University.
College presidents -- North Carolina; Education -- North Carolina -- History -- 19th century; Randolph County (N.C.) -- History; Textbooks -- North Carolina; Trinity College (Randolph County, N.C.) -- History; York, Brantley, 1805-1891; Normal College (Randolph County, N.C.) -- History; Union Institute (Randolph County, N.C.); Duke University -- History; Brown's Schoolhouse (Randolph County, N.C.); Methodist Episcopal Church, South -- Clergy -- North Carolina; Duke University. Presidents
- Brantley York papers, 1838-1950 and undated
  - Documents, 1838-1895 and undated (Oversize-folder 1)
    - "Money received from College, Jan. 6, 1875"
    - Certificate ordaining Brantley York as a Deacon in the North Carolina Conference of the Methodist Episcopal Church, South, Feb. 4, 1838
    - Certificate ordaining Brantley York as a Minister in the North Carolina Conference of the Methodist Episcopal Church, South, Nov. 26, 1848
    - Blank certificate: "Improved System of Teaching, by Rev. Professor B. York. Know all men by these Presents: I Hereby Certify, that _____ has gone through under me a full course of instruction in the English Language, on the Analytical, Constructive and Illustrative System ... I feel no hesitancy in recommending _____ as a Teacher of the English Language...", undated
  - Correspondence, 1841-1910, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes two postcards and one letter written by Bascom A. York, son of Brantley York. Bascom York (1858-1958) was a Methodist minister in N.C.
  - Grade book, 1856-1860 and undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Writings, 1860-1910 and undated
  - The Autobiography of Brantley York, Holograph manuscript, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Autobiography of Brantley York, Typewritten excerpt of Chapter 11, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Published volumes, 1860-1910
    - York, Brantley, 1805-1891. An Illustrative and Constructive Grammar of the English Language. Raleigh, N.C.: Warren L. Pomeroy, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - York, Brantley, 1805-1891. The man of business and railroad calculator, containing such parts of arithmetic as have a special application in business transactions ... by Brantley York; to which are appended a few of the plainer legal forms necessary in ordinary business, prepared by Richard Watt York. Raleigh, N.C.: J. Nichols & Co., 1873. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - York, Brantley, 1805-1891. Introduction to the analytical, synthetical and illustrated grammar; or, A grammar for common schools and beginners: illustrated by several original diagrams, embracing analysis and construction of sentences in familiar lessons, with models, copious exercises and directions, in two parts. Raleigh, N.C.: L. Branson, 1885. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - York, Brantley, 1805-1891. The Autobiography of Brantley York. Durham, N.C.: The Seeman Printery, 1910. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Existence and Location of Copies note
      The Autobiography of Brantley York has been digitized and is available online at the following URL: http://docsouth.unc.edu/nc/york/menu.html
      The digital version of this book is part of the Documenting the American South project at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. Researchers requiring assistance with the digital version should contact this repository directly.
- Material about Brantley York and the York family, 1888-ca. 1900, 1957-1966, 1982, and undated
  - York family genealogy, 1982 and undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Clippings on Brantley York and family [photocopies and transcriptions], 1888-circa 1900, 1957-1966, and undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Clippings (copies and transcripts), 1858, 1891, 1961, 1962, and undated (Oversize-folder 2)